<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: bitcoin | georgepowell.info]]></title>
  <link href="http://georgepowell.info/categories/bitcoin/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://georgepowell.info/"/>
  <updated>2014-05-08T16:17:44+01:00</updated>
  <id>http://georgepowell.info/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[George Powell]]></name>
    <email><![CDATA[georgepowell_1@hotmail.co.uk]]></email>
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Gresham's Law and Bitcoin deflation]]></title>
    <link href="http://georgepowell.info/writing/greshams-law-and-bitcoin-deflation/"/>
    <updated>2014-04-10T12:26:40+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://georgepowell.info/writing/greshams-law-and-bitcoin-deflation</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>You&rsquo;re at the local store buying some bread and milk. The cashier asks you for £3.35. You open your wallet and you&rsquo;ve got two £5 notes:</p>

<h3>Crusty old £5:</h3>

<p><img src="http://i.dailymail.co.uk/i/pix/2011/03/21/article-0-00F3EED2000004B0-407_468x263.jpg" alt="Old note" /></p>

<h3>Crisp new £5:</h3>

<p><img src="http://i.dailymail.co.uk/i/pix/2009/08/24/article-0-00F3EED2000004B0-777_468x249.jpg" alt="New note" /></p>

<p>Which one do you give to the cashier?</p>

<p>Unless you&rsquo;re feeling kind &ndash; that is, you&rsquo;re not an <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Homo_economicus">economic man</a> &ndash; you&rsquo;d want to get rid of your crusty old £5 note; they&rsquo;re worth the same amount to the cashier, so you&rsquo;d be a fool to give up the shiny new one for nothing extra. This is the basis of a paradoxical truth in economics: the measure of a currency&rsquo;s success is if it is used in transactions, yet the <em>shiny, new, better</em> £5 notes will get hoarded while the old ones get traded. <strong>People want to get rid of <em>bad</em> currency, which means it&rsquo;s used more in transactions</strong>. Enter <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gresham's_law">Gresham&rsquo;s Law</a>:</p>

<blockquote><p>Gresham&rsquo;s law is an economic principle that states: &ldquo;When a government overvalues one type of money and undervalues another, the undervalued money will leave the country or disappear from circulation into hoards, while the overvalued money will flood into circulation.&rdquo; It is commonly stated as: &ldquo;Bad money drives out good&rdquo;.</p></blockquote>

<p> We can rewrite the above scenario with bitcoin replacing the new shiny £5 note, and our standard fiat currencies as the old one. Presuming bitcoin is accepted universally and is as easy to pay with as paying by card, which one should you choose?</p>

<p> Bitcoin is digital gold: there is a finite supply. Cash is subject to continuous steady inflation: its value will always be gradually decreasing. So assuming the novelty of spending bitcoin has worn off in this future, it would make sense to keep your value-preserving-bitcoin and get rid of your cash. This is one reason why economists critisise the deflationary (or at least zero-inflation) nature of bitcoin.</p>

<p> The reality is complex, however, and this property doesn&rsquo;t necessarily detract from its other advantages. But this is one reason for believing that even if bitcoin is successful, it won&rsquo;t <em>replace</em> other currencies too easily.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Bitcoin as a product]]></title>
    <link href="http://georgepowell.info/writing/giving-up-on-bitcoin/"/>
    <updated>2014-04-08T14:33:37+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://georgepowell.info/writing/giving-up-on-bitcoin</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><em>Please note I&rsquo;m not an expert on Bitcoin. I write about this stuff for fun.</em></p>

<p>I&rsquo;ve been close to investing in Bitcoin over the past couple of months; its promise as a technology comparable to the internet of 20 years ago is severely tempting. If it ever gains wide acceptence, even a small investment could be worth big money in the coming decades. But I&rsquo;ve given up &ndash; for the moment at least &ndash; on that hope. Here&rsquo;s why:</p>

<h3>Money for the people</h3>

<p>Bitcoin is oft peddled with an economic libertarian ideology. Our fiat currencies are controlled and regulated by the banks and governments, adding fees and friction to transactions. By relying on the system as it is, we hand our power to an unrepresentative minority who can profit from and manipulate our fiat currencies, not necessarily with the majority&rsquo;s best interests in mind. Bitcoin is a decentralised currency that can&rsquo;t be controlled by an individual party, it lets regular folk and small businesses make transactions to each other without needing to trust a third party. This is true, but it&rsquo;s not the whole story.</p>

<h3>The current system</h3>

<p>To gain a real understanding of where bitcoin sits as a technology, we need to understand how the current system works, and what problems (if any) bitcoin solves.</p>

<p>First, lets look at hard cash &ndash; the stuff we carry around in our wallets. Already, cash has some of the essential properties that bitcoin claims: It&rsquo;s untracable, unregulatable, and anonymous; perhaps to a greater extent even than bitcoin. Cash is used for drugs, weapons, money laundering, untaxed income, you name it. Nobody can charge a small business for the right to accept cash. Cash falls down at two hurdles, however: it&rsquo;s not digital, and control of its production is centralised. We&rsquo;ll look at what this really means in a second.</p>

<p>Now lets look at banks and the digitised money they offer through debit and credit cards. By digitising our cash and giving it to the banks, some important things have now changed: it is no longer untracable, anonymous, and unregulatable. By trusting the banks with our money we have sacrificed this for some serious benefits: They keep our money more secure than we could realistically keep cash, they offer fast digital transactions around the world and online, often with no fees or friction, and they offer interest on our savings at no extra cost. The currency is still the same as our cash, so production doesn&rsquo;t change hands. The important thing to realise here is that banks are offering a real service to us in securing and digitising our cash, and in some sense bitcoin must solve a problem not already solved by the combination of modern banking and cash.</p>

<!-- more -->


<h3>Bitcoin as a product</h3>

<p>Finally, lets look at how bitcoin fairs.</p>

<ul>
<li>It&rsquo;s digital. Like the online banking and cards offered by the banks, bitcoin allows transactions to anywhere in the world with the click of a button.</li>
<li>It&rsquo;s pseudoanonymous. In practise, this means that your bitcoin transactions are all tied to a pseudo-identity, which can be in theory unconnected to your real world identity. Although in practise this is hard to achieve without some knowhow in computers. <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=SNssKmeXrGs">Jerry Brito claims in an interview with Vice that you&rsquo;d need to buy bitcoin on the street with cash to guarentee full anonymity.</a></li>
<li>It&rsquo;s decentralised. This removes the need to trust a third party to manage transactions and inflation.</li>
</ul>


<h3>What bitcoin brings to the table</h3>

<p>Let&rsquo;s summarise:</p>

<h5>Bitcoin is</h5>

<ul>
<li>a pseudo-anonymous digital currecy.</li>
<li>a decentralised digital currency.</li>
<li>a completely fee-free digital currency (minus fees to miners)</li>
</ul>


<h5>Bitcoin is not</h5>

<ul>
<li>the only digital currency.</li>
<li>the only anonymous currency.</li>
<li>the only fee-free digital currency, for many transfers/transactions.</li>
</ul>


<p>Naturally, this leads to the question: Why would the average consumer want to switch to bitcoin? Who does bitcoin offer a real service to?</p>

<p>Anonymity is useful for people who don&rsquo;t want to be caught. Bitcoin offers a genuinely useful product for drug dealers, money launderers, and privacy enthusiasts. In these circles bitcoin is already widely used as a currency.</p>

<p>Decentralisation is desirable for those <strong>who don&rsquo;t trust the banks, and don&rsquo;t want the extra services they offer</strong>. A good example of this is when <a href="http://www.wired.com/2010/12/paypal-wikileaks/">paypal froze payments/donations to WikiLeaks</a>, bitcoin cannot in principle be controlled like this and so it became useful as a means to make donations. Bitcoin thrives here when banks/governments fail in the eyes of enough people. Until then, however, in the battle for your digital transactions, banks offer faster transactions, more security, interest on your money, and many other services that bitcoin does not.</p>

<p>Keeping your money in bitcoin means transactions take minutes rather than seconds to authorise, you have complete responsibility over your private-key &ndash; meaning there&rsquo;s no security to fraud and hacking. The government and banks don&rsquo;t respect it, and for the moment at least, most businesses don&rsquo;t accept it.</p>

<p>It&rsquo;s easy to get swept up in the pro-bitcoin mantra, however I struggle to see what bitcoin offers the majority of the population. It&rsquo;s important to analyse the currency as a product competing with what the banks already offer. Who really wants to sacrifice the services, security and regulation offered by the banks in exchange for a difficult to maintain anonymity and a vague feeling of control?</p>

<p>Bitcoin may be an important product to countries who&rsquo;s currencies are failing them, and to those who need anonymity. But bitcoin needs to offer a lot more to gain anything other than a minority acceptance.</p>

<hr />

<h1>&lsquo;Bitcoin banks&rsquo; and regulation</h1>

<p>Writing the above, I&rsquo;d made the assumption that people store all their bitcoins in their personal bitcoin wallets, and there was no such thing as a <em>Bitcoin bank</em>. The analogy goes like this: If your personal bitcoin wallet is like cash, then there can exist a &lsquo;bitcoin bank&rsquo; that provides the desirable services (like security) given by conventional banks but with bitcoin. In theory, this is possible. And it is here where government regulation becomes very relevant.</p>

<p>Google &lsquo;Bitcoin Bank&rsquo; and the first result is <a href="http://flexcoin.com">flexcoin.com</a>. The information on their website is telling&hellip;</p>

<blockquote><p><strong>Flexcoin is shutting down.</strong> On March 2nd 2014 Flexcoin was attacked and robbed of all coins in the hot wallet. The attacker made off with 896 BTC&hellip; As Flexcoin does not have the resources, assets, or otherwise to come back from this loss, we are closing our doors immediately.</p></blockquote>

<p>The &lsquo;bank&rsquo;, existing to provide security and financial services to bitcoin users, ended up doing exactly the opposite and there&rsquo;s nothing that can be done about it; Bitcoin is not regarded as a currency by government and regulatory organisations, and so bitcoin exchanges and banks go unregulated too. Flexcoin is not alone; <a href="http://lyle.smu.edu/~tylerm/fc13.pdf">nearly 50% of all bitcoin exchanges have failed</a>. Look at the <a href="http://www.flexcoin.com/41.html">legal notice on their information page</a>:</p>

<blockquote><p><strong>Legal Notice:</strong> We are not a true bank that accepts USD or any national currency, only bitcoins which by their nature are not regulated, we’re not FDIC insured or regulated by any government entity.</p></blockquote>

<p>With proper regulation on bitcoin banks and exchanges, flexcoin.com might not have been allowed to exist as it did, and maybe some people would have saved their money. It&rsquo;s important to remember here that regulation is <em>for the banks, not the currency</em>, and at least in the ideal case, its purpose is to avoid catastrophes like flexcoin and MtGox.</p>

<p>Bitcoin banks may in theory be able to provide the same services as conventional banks, but current attempts have widely failed, especially when it comes to security. This is a product of the decentralised and unregulated nature of bitcoin, so time will tell if innovative companies can provide sufficient services to make bitcoin as usable. But the hurdles of regulation and security have yet to be passed.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
