<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: maths | georgepowell.info]]></title>
  <link href="http://georgepowell.info/categories/maths/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://georgepowell.info/"/>
  <updated>2014-04-17T12:12:38+01:00</updated>
  <id>http://georgepowell.info/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[George Powell]]></name>
    <email><![CDATA[georgepowell_1@hotmail.co.uk]]></email>
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Maths ain't magic]]></title>
    <link href="http://georgepowell.info/writing/maths-aint-magic/"/>
    <updated>2014-04-16T23:23:56+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://georgepowell.info/writing/maths-aint-magic</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h1>Imaginary numbers and the nature of mathematics</h1>

<p>I first heard of imaginary numbers when someone showed me the <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mandelbrot_set">Mandelbrot Set</a>:</p>

<p><img src="https://lh4.googleusercontent.com/-nnOUsGwmsEw/AAAAAAAAAAI/AAAAAAAAAAA/xgyUbcFMo6g/photo.jp" alt="Mandelbrot visualisation" /></p>

<p>They described it to me:</p>

<blockquote><p>The x axis is for the real numbers, and the y axis is for the imaginary numbers. The colour of each pixel is determined by the properties of the imaginary and real numbers it represents.</p></blockquote>

<p>My reaction was confusion, as it should have been. That picture sure doesn&rsquo;t look imaginary. And how can these numbers exist on a computer if they&rsquo;re imaginary? Maybe I&rsquo;m not smart enough to understand, maybe it&rsquo;s a concept only accessible to the minds of mathematitions. What are imaginary numbers?</p>

<blockquote><p>Well&hellip; They&rsquo;re <em>made up</em> numbers that don&rsquo;t really exist like normal numbers do. There&rsquo;s <strong>no</strong> number that can be squared into a negative number, so we make up the imaginary numbers!</p></blockquote>

<p>I learnt to program in my teens and when I <a href="http://www.newgrounds.com/portal/view/501340">wrote my own mandelbrot set visualiser</a> I realised it doesn&rsquo;t really need <em>imaginary-made-up</em> numbers after all. All it needs is two standard real numbers and a formula.</p>

<p>What&rsquo;s &lsquo;imaginary&rsquo; about imaginary numbers then? Well &lsquo;real&rsquo; negative numbers don&rsquo;t have &lsquo;real&rsquo; square roots, so we call their roots &lsquo;imaginary&rsquo;. It&rsquo;s a <em>name</em>. Are they more imaginary that the &lsquo;real&rsquo; numbers? No. You don&rsquo;t need a special type of calculator or a special kind of pen to calculate with imaginary numbers. It&rsquo;s really not the best naming decision: calling a fundamental and useful concept &lsquo;imaginary&rsquo; scares and confuses people away from trying to understand it. The crux to understanding imaginary numbers is to realise how normal and unimaginary they really are.</p>

<p>Mathematics studies <em>formal abstractions</em> &ndash; mental constructions that have been defined so carefully and unambiguously that their properties become objective. 1, 2, 3 and the rest of the counting numbers, they&rsquo;re all abstractions: concepts we create to categorise, percieve and understand the world. We use abstractions to represent things, and whether abstractions are &lsquo;real&rsquo; or not doesn&rsquo;t even matter; <em>they&rsquo;re all as real or unreal as each other</em>. Imaginary numbers exist alongside all the real numbers as mathematical abstractions, and useful tools to represent the world we live in.</p>

<p>It&rsquo;s the way the mind works. We develop concepts and abstractions to represent the world and its behaviour &ndash; mathematics studies the subset of these concepts that have been formally defined. To know <em>what infinity is</em>, or <em>what an imaginary number is</em>, is really just knowing how the mind uses abstractions to represent our surroundings.</p>

<p>The view that mathematics is just concepts and abstractions in our psychology is far from the only accepted philosophy. There&rsquo;s <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Philosophy_of_mathematics#Contemporary_schools_of_thought">plenty of schools of thought</a> around what maths is. For me, however, any <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Platonism">existential or borderline-spiritual</a> view of mathematical knowledge has caused more confusion and  gotten in the way of learning the actual maths.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
